Guide to the Brown & Root / George R. Brown Executive Files, 1937-1978 MS 488
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Brown & Root / George R. Brown Executive Files
1937-1978
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Brown & Root, Inc.
MS 488
24 Linear Feet (46 boxes)
0.768 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0488aip_001 (0.768 GB)
The bulk of this material consists of business records of the Brown & Root firm and Brown Shipbuilding Co., relating in particular to building projects and joint ventures with other companies such as Zapata Offshore, Texas Gulf Sulphur and ARMCO Steel, as well as internal operations of the firm. Formats include correspondence, internal memos, project site drawings, photographs, reports, notes, and newsclippings.
Organizational Sketch
In 1914, native Texan Herman Brown was given eighteen mules in lieu of back wages for construction work done in his hometown of Belton, which he used to enter the construction business on his own. In 1919 his brother-in-law, Dan Root, advanced him money for working capital, and the company was named Brown and Root, Incorporated. In 1922 Herman's younger brother, George Rufus Brown, joined the firm. Dan Root, a prosperous Central Texas cotton farmer, died in 1929. The paving of dirt roads and building of steel bridges for municipal and county governments in Central Texas led the firm to a successful joint bid in 1936 to construct the Marshall Ford Dam (now Mansfield Dam) on the Colorado River. A 1940 contract to construct the Corpus Christi Naval Air Station was the first of their big federal war projects. The brothers formed the Brown Shipbuilding Company in 1942 and constructed more than 350 vessels for the navy. The shipyard had a labor force of 25,000 and won the Army-Navy E and a presidential citation.
After World War II the Brown brothers and other investors purchased the Big and Little Inch pipelines from the government with the winning high bid of $143 million and organized a new company, Texas Eastern Transmission Company, which is now a part of Panhandle Eastern Corporation. Brown and Root was widely known during the 1950s and 1960s for constructing United States air and naval bases (in Spain, France, and Guam) and roads, dams, bridges, petrochemical plants, and large offshore drilling platforms. In 1961 the company won the planning contract for the $200 million Manned Spacecraft Center in Houston.
Herman Brown died on November 15, 1962, and was buried in Glenwood Cemetery, Houston.Brown was a cofounder of the Brown Foundation. He was a member of the board of directors of First City National Bank of Houston, Texas Eastern Transmission Corporation, Southwestern University, Armco Steel Corporation, and Texas Children's Hospital in Houston. He was also active in oil and gas exploration and ranching.
After the death of his brother Herman in 1962, George became president of Brown and Root. Later that year the corporation was sold to the Halliburton Company.
In December 1962 the Halliburton Company of Dallas purchased Brown and Root, which continues to operate under its own name. Halliburton's significant acquisition of Brown and Root of Houston in 1962 gained for the company the sort of subsudiaries that heretofore had been missing: industrial and marine engineering and construction firms. At the time of acquisition Brown and Root had annual revenues of $5.5 billion.
George R. Brown served as a director of the Halliburton Company, Armco Steel Corporation, Louisiana Land and Exploration Company, International Telephone and Telegraph Corporation, Trans-World Airlines, Southland Paper Company, First City Bancorporation, and Highland Oil Company. He served on important commissions for presidents Truman, Eisenhower, Kennedy, and Johnson, and was appointed to commissions for the state of Texas, from the 1930s under Governor James Allred to the 1970s under Governor Dolph Briscoe. He was a well-known friend and visible supporter of Lyndon B. Johnson throughout his political career. He was the recipient of many honors during his lifetime, including Awards from Rice University, Colorado School of Mines, Southwestern University, and the University of Texas. He received several awards in construction and engineering, including the John Fritz Medal in 1977 from the five national engineering societies, and the American Petroleum Institute Gold Medal.
Brown served as chairman of the board of trustees of Rice University for fifteen years of his twenty-five years of service on the board. In 1951 the Brown brothers and their wives established the Brown Foundation, through which they pursued a strong and generous interest in philanthropy. By June 30, 1994, the foundation had granted more than $381 million to charitable institutions, primarily in higher education and the arts. In 1925 Brown married Alice Nelson Pratt of Lometa, Texas, who became well-known for her support for the arts at the local, state, and national levels. They had three children. Brown died on January 22, 1983, and was buried in Glenwood Cemetery, Houston.
"BROWN, GEORGE RUFUS." and "BROWN, HERMAN". The Handbook of Texas Online. http://www.tsha.utexas.edu/handbook/online/articles/view/BB/fbrbg.html [Accessed Mon Jul 14 12:01:07 US/Central 2003 ].
Scope and Contents
The bulk of this material consists of business records of the Brown & Root firm and the Brown Shipbuilding Co., relating in particular to building projects and joint ventures with other companies as well as internal operations of the firm. Formats include correspondence, internal memos, project site drawings, photographs, reports, notes, and newsclippings.
Some specific projects include various international airbases, Marshall Ford Dam, Pedernales River Electric Cooperative, City of Houston roads and water, Rice Institute, Mohole Project, and many others. Correspondents include individuals and other companies such as ARMCO Steel, Construction Management & Engineering Associates (CMEA), Harlan Inc., Pre-stressed Concrete Products, Inc., Southland Paper Mills, Inc., Texas Eastern Transmission Corp, Texas Gulf Sulphur Co., and the U.S. Navy and Dept. of Defense.
Folder titles are original Brown & Root titles.
Digital Scholarship Archive
Portions of this collection are available online at https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/37263
Accruals
No future additions are expected for this material.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Halliburton, 1999.
Related Materials
See also MS 464, Builders: Herman & George R. Brown Book Research Files.
Custodial History
This material was formerly housed in the Information Resource Center of Kellogg Brown & Root.
Restrictions on Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital files in archival information package format (MS0488aip_001) on nearline server. Contact woodson@rice.edu for access.
Index Terms
Subjects
Roads -- Design and construction; Dams -- Design and construction; Gas industry -- United States; Concrete construction -- History; Construction industry -- Texas -- History; Offshore oil field equipment industry
Document Types
Maps; memorandums; photographs; reports; corrrespondence; clippings (information artifacts)
Places
Marshall Ford Dam (Colorado River, Tex.)
Subjects (Persons)
Brown, Herman,1892-1962; Brown, George R., 1898-1983
Subjects (Corporations)
Brown & Root, Inc.; Armco Steel Corporation; Brown Shipbuilding Company, Inc.; Pre-stressed Concrete Products, Inc.; Southland Paper Mills (Lufkin, Tex.); Texas Gulf Sulphur Company, inc; Panhandle Eastern Corporation; Brown & Root, Inc.; KBR (Firm)
- Series I: Brown Root Subject Files, 1939-1978, bulk 1950s; 18.5 feet (37 boxes)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, reports, notes, brochures, site drawings and contracts related to Brown & Root projects, proposed projects and issues such as energy and constructions resources and labor. Some specific projects include various international airbases, Marshall Ford Dam, Pedernales River Electric Cooperative, City of Houston roads and water, Rice Institute, Mohole Project, and many others. Correspondents include individuals and other companies such as ARMCO Steel, Construction Management & Engineering Associates (CMEA), Harlan Inc., Southland Paper Mills, Inc., Texas Eastern Transmission Corp, Texas Gulf Sulphur Co., and the U.S. Navy and Dept. of Defense. Folder titles are original Brown & Root titles.
  - Airbases (drawings and minimal correspondence)
    - Bordeaux-Merignac Airbase St. Nazaire Airbase, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Chateauroux Complex, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Chaumont Airbase, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Chambley Airbase, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Etain-Rouvres Airbase, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dreux –Louvilliers Airbase, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Evreux-Fauville Airbase, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Laon-Couvron Airbase, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Niort Area, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Phalsbourg Airbase, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - St. Mihiel Area, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Spanish airbases, 1954-1958 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Toul-Rosiers Airbase, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - AIRCO Industrial Gases settlement on AIRCO cylinders, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Alaskan Ventures: Proposed projects and correspondence, 1958-68 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Alleghany Corp., 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Allied Sheet Metal Roofing, 1951-1956 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - ARMCO Steel – Misc., 1954 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - ARMCO Steel – Misc., 1955 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - ARMCO Steel – Sheffield Steel, 1950-1954 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - ARMCO Steel – Misc., 1956 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - ARMCO Steel – Misc. corresp., 1959 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - ARMCO Steel – Corresp., 1966 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - ARMCO Steel – Corresp., 1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - ARMCO Steel 1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - ARMCO Steel 1970 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Associated companies and/or subsidiaries, 1949-1954 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Bloomfield Steamship Co., 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Business Council, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Canadian River Project (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Carbide Chemical job, Seadrift, TX (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Century Investment Co. – WTB Corp., 1939-1956 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Chemical Petroleum Division, F.W. Bell thru 1950 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Century Investment Co. – WTB Corp., Plaza Hotel, 1939-1956 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Chemical Petroleum Division, F.W. Bell (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Edward Clark legislative matters/labor troubles, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - Edward Clark legislative/labor, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Construction Management Engineering Associates (CMEA)
    - General, 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Misc. corresp., 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Weekly reports, minutes of other meetings, 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Drawings, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Unsafe installations – France, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
    - Unsafe installations – France, comparisons (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - The French Construction Industry and Its Capacity to Execute the Military Program (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Construction Management and Engineering Associates Organization (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Monthly reports, Nov.-Dec. 1952, Jan.-Aug. 1953, Paris, France (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Corpus Christi misc., 1945-1956 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Darneille, George – misc. memos, deals, 1951-1956 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Driskill Hotel, 1955-1959 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - El Paso Building and Construction Trades Council vs. TX Highway Commission, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Florida oil deal – Virgil Osborn, 1941-1956 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Foreign, Italy – ANIC corresp., 1955-1958 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Frost Lumber Co. (Olin Industries), 1951 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Guam: Brown-Pacific-Maxon, 1946-1954 (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
  - Halliburton Co. corresp., 1969 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Harlan Inc. Board of Directors meetings, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Harlan Inc.: Harlan-Doherty (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Harlan Inc.: Fred S. James Co. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Harlan Inc. proposed public offering, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Harlan Inc. reports of competitors (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Highlands Insurance Co.
    - Benrus Corp. (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Crum Forster (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Employers Casualty Co.; Southwestern Life Insurance Co. (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Prudential-Skandia-Hudson (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - San Jacinto River Authority (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Southern Marine Aviation Underwriters (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Hong Kong and Shanghai Banking Corp. overdraft agreement – Kuwait Br., 1965-1968 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - City of Houston Main Street reports, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - City of Houston water corresp., 1939-1940 (Box 13, Folder 2-3)
  - City of Houston water, 1939-1940s (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Humble Oil Refining Co. general corresp., 1955-1968 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Hurricane Betsy loans, 1965-1967 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - International Telephone Telegraph Corp. (IT (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - IT (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - IT (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Jetero ranch property site, 1957-1961 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Kitcat Aitken, 1971-1972 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Labor corresp., pamphlets, 1958-1961 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Labor suit against unions, 1950-1952 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Larson, Jess, 1957-1961 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - LeDuc Southern Absorption Ltd., 1953 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - W.H. Leslie – memos, misc. letters, 1957 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - W.H. Leslie – Minor Hudson corresp., 1949 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Lone Star Steel Co., 1951-1952 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Lone Star Steel Corp., 1959-1960 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Longview paving job, 1939 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Louisiana Bridge Co. – misc. corresp., 1957-1959 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Louisiana Land Exploration Co., 1969 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Maner Lake and Eagle Nest Lake, Brazoria Development Assoc., 1944-61 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Marble Falls Ranch, Travis Co., TX, 1959 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Marsh, Charles E., 1947-1956 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Marshall Ford Dam
    - Balance sheet showing working fund, 1938 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Balance sheet showing working fund, 1940 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Balance sheet operating statement, 1940-41 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Herman Brown (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Contracts (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Equipment (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Insurance (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
    - Labor costs and wage rates (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Lumber, sand, gravel, steel, cement, concrete, etc. (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Personnel (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Statement of costs, 1940-1941 (Box 18, Folder 2-3)
    - Stone and rock production (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - McKinney, Robert – Corresp., articles, 1957-1961 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Mining Metallurgical Division, Domingo Moreno H. Monroe, 1952- 1956 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Mining Metallurgical Division (NY) (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Mohole Project progress reports, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Mohole Project, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 2-3)
  - Mohole Project, 1963 (Box 19, Folder 4-5)
  - Mohole Project termination, 1966-1968 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Mohole Project – general and administrative overhead (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - National politics (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - New Orleans property deal – Brown-Utah-DeMontluzin, 1958- (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Oltorf, Frank, misc. Washington corresp., 1951-1956 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Palomas Ranch: Corresp. and statements, 1950-1954 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Pedernales Electric Cooperative job, Johnson City, 1939 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Piermain Corp., 1955-1956 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Pima Mine, 1952-1956 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - President's Materials Policy Commission, 1951-1952
    - Manual, 1951 (Box 21, Folder 4-5)
    - Resources for Freedom, V. II, 1952 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Mr. Brown Part II, "Strengthening Our Domestic Resource Base," Chap. I-III, Jan. 15-18, 1952 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Mr. Brown Part III, "Strengthening the Free World Resource Base," Chp. I-VIII, Jan. 15-18, 1952 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Mr. Brown Part V-VI, "Strengthening the Energy Resource Base," Jan. 15-18, 1952 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Various chapters, 1952 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Photos from report, taken Feb. 11, 1952 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Pre-stressed Concrete Products (PCP), Inc. board meetings, Jan. 1957-65 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - PCP reports on Mandeville properties, 1964 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - PCP, 1968 (Box 23, Folder 3-4)
  - PCP retirement and savings statements, 1968 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - PCP – J.E. Walters bonus and relating paper, 1960s (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Proposed projects
    - New Mexico Los Alamos job, 1943-49; Oak Ridge, 1952 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Rock crushing operation in Florida, 1955 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Foreign work, 1955-1956 (Box 24, Folder 3-4)
    - Company business/projects, 19566 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Company business/projects, 1957 (Box 24, Folder 6-7)
    - Company business/projects, 1957 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - General corresp., 1957-1961 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Company business/projects (Box 25, Folder 3-4)
    - Prospective work, 1961-1962 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Rice Institute
    George R. Brown served as chairman of the board of trustees of Rice University for fifteen years of his twenty-five years of service on the board.
    - Budget, audit and financial reports, 1954-1956 (Box 25, Folder 6-7)
    - Budget and financial statements, corresp., 1948-1957 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Cinder track, 1955 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Property owned and acquired, Rice Lumber Co., 1953-1956 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Research-Nuclear Reactor High Voltage Lab, 1951-1953 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Research-Nuclear Reactor High Voltage Lab, 1955-1956 (Box 26, Folder 5-6)
    - Stadium, 1951-1955 (Box 27, Folder 1-2)
    - Stadium financing, 1949-1955 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Stadium labor trouble, 1950-1951 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Stocks and bonds, 1953-1956 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Paul O. Sims Co.; Herman Brown property, addition 1, Austin, 1949 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Paul O. Sims Co.; Herman Brown property, addition 2, Austin (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Slidell-Little Woods Bridge, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Charles P. Smith, 1939-1940 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Sonic Research Corp., 1957 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Southern Natural Gas Co., 1956 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Southern Sales Transportation Co., 1957-1958 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Southland Paper Mills, Inc., 1943-1956 (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Southland Paper Mills, Inc., 1943-1956 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Southland Paper Mills, Inc., 1957-1960 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Southland Paper Mills, Inc. corresp., 1965 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Southland Paper Mills, Inc., 1969 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Southland Paper Mills, Inc., 1970 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Steel liner work for containment structures, 1977 (Box 30, Folder 1-3)
  - Steel liner work for containment structures, 1978 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Tank machining project, 1951-1953 (Box 30, Folder 5-6)
  - Tennessee Gas Transmission Co., 1958-1961 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Texas Co., 1958-1961 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Texas Eastern Transmission Corp. corresp., 1966 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Texas Eastern Transmission Corp. corresp., 1967 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Texas Gulf Sulphur Co. misc. corresp., 1952-1956 (Box 31, Folder 3-4)
  - Texas Gulf Sulphur Co. misc. corresp, 1957-1961 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Texas Gulf Sulphur Co. proposed centralization of all ship and barge loading facilities, San Leon, TX, 1957 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Texas Gulf Sulphur Co. – Fred Nelson's underwater drilling platform invention, 1953 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Texas Railroad Commission, 1957-1959 (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Texas Railway Equipment Co., 1957-1960 (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - Thomas, Albert, 1946-1961 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Thompson, Ernest O. – misc. statutes, Point Barrow trip 1952-1956 (Box 32, Folder 2-3)
  - Thompson, Ernest O. – Point Barrow inspection trip, 1953-1956 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Timcoat Corp., 1957-1960 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Trans World Airlines, Inc. corresp., 1969 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Umlauf, Charles, sculpture of George R. Brown – photos, 1953 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Underwood, Neuhaus Co., Inc. Offshore Industry Seminar, 1968 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Union Carbide Co. corresp. and reports, 1959-1961 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - United Carbon Co., 1960 (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - United Carbon India contract file, 1960s (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - United Carbon India Ltd. financial matters, 1960s (Box 33, Folder 6-7)
  - United Carbon India Ltd., 1960s (Box 34, Folder 1-2)
  - United Carbon India personnel, 1960s (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - United Carbon India – J.B. Davenport reports, 1964-1965 (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - U.S. Dept. of Defense Industry Advisory Council, 1968 (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Dept. of Defense Industry Advisory Council, 1969 (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - U.S. Navy Ammunition Depot, McAllester, OK
    - Brown and Bellows firms corresp., 1942-1943 (Box 35, Folder 1-2)
    - Contract Noy-5691, 1942-1944 (Box 35, Folder 3-5)
  - U.S. Dept. of the Navy, 1963 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Ultrasonic Inspection Device (Frank E. Richardson), 1952 (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Valentine Pulp Paper Co. misc. corresp., 1957-1958 (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Valentine Pulp Paper Co. corresp., 1962 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Venezuela
    - GRB South American trip as guest of Creole Petroleum Corp., 1954 (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - Jobs, 1957 (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - Raymond Concrete Pile Co.-B (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - Proposed Maracaibo bridge, 1956-1957 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Vitro Corp. of America, 1962 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Walters, J.E., 1949-1951 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - William A. Smith Construction Co., 1967-1968 (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Wolf, Monroe, 1963-1964 (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Womack, Frank, 1939-1940 (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - John L. Wortham Son, 1968 (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - H.B. Zachry Co. contract, 1960s (Box 37, Folder 8)
  - Zapata Offshore Co., 1968-1969 (Box 37, Folder 9)
- Series II: Brown Root Legal Files, 1937-1961; (0.5 linear ft., 1 box)
  Notes, correspondence, and several briefs related to Brown & Root legal claims and suits.
  - Legal claims and suits, 1957-1961 (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Legislation correspondence, 1961 (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Herman Brown v. O.L. Neyland, 1940 [?], brief for appellants (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Brown Root v. A.F.L. Beaumont, correspondence, 1949-50 (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - J.C. Jacques v. Brown Root, brief for defendant, 1937-39 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Trusts: George R. Brown; Austin, Lucy Ann and Elizabeth Booth, Thomas Margaret Brown; Margaret Ann Paden, Mary James Root, 1946 (Box 38, Folder 6)
- Series III: Brown Root General Office Files, 1955-70; (1.5 linear ft., 3 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Experience records and qualifications (misc. B (Box 39, Folder 2-3)
  - Incentive bonus / fund
    - 1955-58 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - 1959 (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - 1960-62 (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - 1965 (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - 1966 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - 1968 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - India Company – Proposed (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Institute on U.S. Taxation of Foreign Income, Inc. (Box 40, Folder 8)
  - Insurance Dept.
    - 1962-66 (Box 40, Folder 9)
    - 1967-69 (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Insurance Manager, 1966-70 (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - Personnel, 1957-61 (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - Policy and Procedure, 1957-61 (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - U.S. Internal Revenue Audit, International Operations Agent, 1960-68 (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - Wage Salary information
    - 1964-68 (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - 1969-70 (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Workmen's Compensation, 1965-70 (Box 42, Folder 2)
- Series IV: Herman Brown Personal Correspondence, 1960-61; (0.25 linear ft., 2 folders)
  - 1960 (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - 1961 (Box 42, Folder 4)